<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The recoverie of paradise. A sermon, on the incarnation and birth of our Sauior Christ. By Michael Birkhed</title>
            <author>Birkenhead, Michael.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73518</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3088.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125282</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900563</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900563</idno>
            <idno type="VID">133395</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73518)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 133395)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2059:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The recoverie of paradise. A sermon, on the incarnation and birth of our Sauior Christ. By Michael Birkhed</title>
                  <author>Birkenhead, Michael.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 63, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nicholas Ling and Thomas Bushel, and are by them to be sold,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D E² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christmas sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Incarnation --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:133395:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133395:1"/>
            <p>THE RECOVERIE of Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>A Sermon, on the Incarnation and Birth of our Sauior Chriſt.</p>
            <p>By Michael Birkhed.</p>
            <q>Mercy and Truth are met together, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and Peace haue kiſſed each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. lxxxv. verſe x.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed for Nicholas Ling and Thomas Buſhel, and are by them to be ſold. 1602.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:133395:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133395:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable, <hi>Sir Tho. Egerton Knight,</hi> Lord Keeper of the great Seale of England, and one of hir Maieſties <hi>moſt Honorable Priuy</hi> Counſell.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath bin (Right Honorable) well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated amongſt the Learned, where Learning was firſt profeſſed, and it is as truly recorded of many worthy Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, who were the firſt that did teach for to Write, and ſurely as our forefathers did reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence them as Gods, which ſpake wiſedome; ſo we may extol them as men ſomewhat ſuperior vnto men which inuented the arte to Write what they ſpake. The firſt benefitted the perſons that heard them; by the latter are inſtructed al poſterities that ſhall reade them: the one inſtructed thoſe onely that were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with them, the other gaue leſſons vnto all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whatſoeuer, though neuer ſo much diſtant from them. And therefore very well ſaith a certaint Poet, nowe liuing:</p>
            <lg>
               <l>O bleſſed letters that combine in one,</l>
               <l>All ages paſt, and make one liue with all:</l>
               <l>By you we do confer with thoſe are gone,</l>
               <l>And the dead-liuing vnto Counſell call,</l>
               <l>By you the vnborne ſhall haue communion,</l>
               <l>Of what we feele, and what doth vs befall.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>The conſideration of which premiſes, together with the reſpect of this ouer-fruitfull age of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb facs="tcp:133395:3"/> of the Prophets, the Land hauing more Church men then Churches, and more Preachers then Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes to Preach in; hath moued me (though leaſt of the Apoſtles yet vnwilling to hide my talent with the vnprofitable ſeruant) to write what I haue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore ſpoken, and to publiſh what I haue Written, which I proſtrate as my free-will offring at the foote of the Aulter, as the poore Iſraelites did their Goats haire, when they had no better to bring, and as the Widdow did hir mite, when ſhe had nothing greater to giue. And foraſmuch as Curteſie is the true note of Gentilitie, and Learning is beſt fauoured of ſuch as are beſt Learned, and matters of Religion of thoſe that are Religious; I haue therefore made choyſe of your Honor for Patron of theſe papers, not doubting, but that in regard of Gentilitie, you will curteouſly receiue it, in reſpect of your Learning, willingly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vſe it, and for the matter and ſubiect of it, Patronize and protect it. Your Lordſhips fauourable entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this, ſhall encourage me in greater matters hereafter to imploy my Labors vnto the memoriall of your worthines: and mooue others to peruſe it the more diligently, being entertained of a Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of ſuch Honour and Iudgement. Thus, wiſhing vnto your Lordſhip, the accompliſhment of your wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, crauing pardon for my (perhappes) ouermuch boldnes, I humbly take my leaue, this firſt of Ianuary.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors to commaund. Michaell Birkhed.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:133395:3"/>
            <head>THE RECOVERY of Paradiſe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Luke. 2. 10.</bibl>
               <q>Feare not: for behold I bring you tidings of great ioy that ſhall be vnto all People. That is, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you is borne this day in the Citty of Dauid a Sauiour which is Christ the Lord.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reat is the Solemnitie of this feaſt of Chriſt his Natiuity, but the ſhortneſſe of the day, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth to reade but a ſhort diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe: and no maruell if the words we write be ſhort, ſeeing God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made, as at this time his word (the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of this booke) very ſhort. If you would knowe the ſhortneſſe of Gods <hi>Word;</hi> behold that <hi>Word</hi> which ſaid by his Prophet, <hi>I fill both Heauen and Earth,</hi> which was neither <hi>Included in any thing, nor excluded out of any thing, but was all in euery thing,</hi> euen that <hi>Word</hi> which <hi>the Heauen of heauens could not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine,</hi> which was, <hi>from euerlaſting without beginning</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:133395:4"/> 
               <hi>or ending.</hi> Was now included in a place, ſwadled in cloutes, laied vp in a cratch, and become a child of a dayes age: a long word indeed, become very ſhort; and yet what length of time, or multiplication of words is able to deſcipher, the incomprehenſible length and breadth thereof? for euen in his humilitie, his glorie is exalted, and in the ſhortneſſe of his name, his name is enlarged. Great are the works of the Lord, as himſelfe is great, but greateſt is that which he did in his little one. <hi>Paruulus nobis venerit, ſed non parum attulit, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> parum nobis contulit. He came as a little one, but he brought not a little with him, it was no little benefit he did vs.</hi> It is no vnknowne thing to him that knoweth any thing: how glorious was the eſtate of Adam in paradiſe, being created in the Image of the God of glory, liuing in a place of all kinde of pleaſure, vnder the ſhade of the tree of life, with a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion that was meet &amp; fit for him, Inioying the ſight of God himſelfe, whoſe countenance is the fulnes of al ioyes &amp; felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, nothing being forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, that might any wiſe delight him, ſaue onely the fruite of one tree that was in the midſt of the garden: the penalty, if he taſted of it, was the expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing out of paradiſe, the depriuation of his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:133395:4"/> pleaſures, death &amp; damnation to his body &amp; ſoule, &amp; euerlaſting miſeries to either amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the diuels in hell-fire. But what followed? <hi>Thy princes</hi> (ſaith Eſay) <hi>were rebellious and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions of theeues.</hi> Our parents di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſobeyed the charge of the Almighty, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied Lucifer in his the euery of Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſo became ſubiect vnto the forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med damnation. Great was their fault ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately to haue ſinned, and great was the puniſhment that was inflicted for their ſin. For the <hi>Earth mourneth for it, yea euen vnto the children</hi> (as Zoroaſtes ſpeaketh.) Though the father did onely eate the ſowre grape, yet his childrens teeth are alſo ſet on edge by it: ſo that we were <hi>Damnati antequam nati.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to die, euen before wee beganne to liue. Glorious was mans condition beeing created in Gods Image, but better had it bin that he had neuer bin created, then ſo to haue defaced the glory of that Image. But as God is the happieſt and chiefeſt good, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all happines and goodnes in himſelfe, ſo ſuch was his loue and fauour towards man, that he would make him partaker alſo of that his happines, and therefore preſently he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him a medicine for his malady, and a ſalue for his ſore, namely, that as Sathan had
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:133395:5"/> deiected him into the pit of hell, ſo his ſonne ſhould erect and lift him vp into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, if he would belieue in the one, as he had giuen credite to the other. Falſhood had ſeduced and deceiued him, and Truth muſt reduce and inſtruct him, yet ſo, that after he know the Truth, hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce falſhood, and cleaue vnto the Truth: this Truth was that word: this word was that Sonne: this Sonne was that Sauiour, <hi>which was made ſhort, became little, and was borne as this day in the Citty of Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leſt this ſo precious and peereleſſe a Iem ſhould lie hid in the dunghill, and be in the world, and the world know him not, it pleaſed the Lord by many ſignes and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, by many Propheſies and prefigurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to deſcribe him plainely vnto all poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that none might aledge Ignorance for an excuſe of their wickedneſſe. Therefore his ſtarre was ſhewne vnto the wiſemen of the Eaſt, by the conduct whereof they came from the riſing of the Sunne, to the citty of Hieruſalem, to ſignifie that a new Sonne of Righteouſneſſe was riſen in the Earth, who by his bright &amp; reſplendent beames ſhould inlighten and delight euery one that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth into the world: many rare and prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:133395:5"/> things alſo were ſeene at that time euen amongſt the Infidels and Heathen people, declaring the Reſtauration of the world, the Reſtitution of man, the Solace of the Iewe, &amp; the Saluation, &amp; Redemption of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde to be come into the world. For as <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſius</hi> reporteh out of a certrine ſtreete in Roome there ſprung vp a fountaine of oyle, which flowed moſt aboundantly for the ſpace of a whole day, and alſo (which is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be noted) though the Romane Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour had obtained the Scepter of the whole world, and a generall peace was concluded, ſo that the Temple Ianus was ſhut vp cloſe (a thing ſcarce euer ſeene before.) Yet <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus</hi> forbad that any ſhould call him Lord, not without the wondering of all that heard it, and about that time he ſet at liberty 30000. bond-ſlaues which had fled from their Lords, (being prouoked no doubt) by the motion and Inſtinction of God himſelfe: Theſe things did God ordaine to be done in the Imperiall citty, euen in the citty of the Earths Emperour, to declare vnto the world that the mediator of mankinde, the Oyle of Gladneſſe, the Prince of peace, was come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world; vnto whom the title of Lord, is onely, or moſt rightly to be attributed, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:133395:6"/> he is the true deliuerer of miſerable man, the Vaſſall and Bond-ſlaue of Sinne, flying from God, from life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and from Heauen vnto Hel, vnto Death &amp; the ſeruice of the Diuel, and reſtoreth him vnto his true Lord and Maiſter againe, that ſo being freed from Sin, and made the ſeruant of God, hee might at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto Liberty of the Angels in Heauen. What neede I recite many Records hereof, ſeeing God did point at him, and diſtinctly name him: the Angels came &amp; miniſtred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, millions of men did heare him &amp; ſee him: &amp; the very diuels of Hell did acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and confeſſe him. But of all manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that is none of the obſcureſt that was ſhewne the very night of his Natiuity vnto the ſhepheards of Iurie, which we haue cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen for the ground-worke of this booke, and the foundation of our writing. An Hiſtory which will bring you like the Wiſemens ſtarre vnto the place of his Birth, and an Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, which if you marke it, wil vnfold vnto you, the fruites of his Birth.</p>
            <q>Feare not: for behold, I bring you tidings of great ioy which ſhal be vnto all People. That is, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you is borne this day in the Citty of Dauid a Sauiour, which is Christ the Lord.</q>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:133395:6"/>
            <p> Theſe wordes are an Epitomy or ſhort ſum of the whole Booke of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taining the long expected Tydings of mans happy ſaluation in Ieſus Chriſt. They were vttered as (I ſaied) vnto certaine ſhepheards of Iury, Shepheards that were faithfully attending their flockes in the fields, being the true Reſemblance of gods ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all paſtors, and faithfull miniſters, and that by an Angell ſent as a ſolemne Embaſſadour from the Court of Heauen. The ſumme of whoſe meſſage was this. That God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the wretched eſtate, of his woefull creatures and the damnable condition of the ſons of Adam, how they lay ſweltring in their fathers goare, how they ſtuck faſt in the mire and clay, and were not able to Recouer the tree of Life, from which they had fallen, but continued ſubiect vnto the Doome of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which, by the Law, there was no Redemption, without ſatisfaction for their fathers tranſgreſſion. That therefore God of his mercy, not vnmindefull of his promiſe that he had made vnto Adam. <hi>That the ſeede of the Woman ſhould breake the ſerpents Head.</hi> Which alſo, by an oth he had ratified vnto Abraham viz: <hi>That in his ſeed all the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Earth ſhoulde bee bleſſed.</hi> Had now
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:133395:7"/> ſent his ſon from Heauen into earth to bring man fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth into Heauen vnto him; &amp; that by beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming Sin for Man though he knew no ſinne, that man might be made the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of God in him. And therefore that they needed not to feare the death &amp; damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that was due vnto them for their Fathers tranſgreſſions, but with Ioyfull harts ſhould embrace the Life and Saluation that was comming vnto them by the ſonne of Gods Incarnation, in whom whoſoeuer beleeued ſhould not periſh, but haue life euerlaſting.</p>
            <q>Feare not: for behold I bring you tidings of great Ioy which ſhalbe vnto, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>The words as you may ſee do generally containe an argument vnto encouragement, and in it more perticularly I obſerue theſe 3. partes. Firſt the encouragement it ſelfe, in theſe words, <hi>Fare not.</hi> Secondly, the reaſon of it, <hi>for I bring you Tidings of Ioy.</hi> Thirdly, the ioyfull tidings what it was, in theſe words, <hi>vnto you is borne this day in the Citty of Dauid, &amp;c.</hi> And firſt of the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Feare not]</hi> As the comfortableſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort that Adam receiued in his Paradiſe of pleaſure was the pleaſant fruition of his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:133395:7"/> Creators preſence, it being repleniſhed with all ioyes and conſolations: So ſince his fall, like a guilty malefactor, he hath ſhunned no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then that his ſight &amp; preſence, and therefore as ſoone as euer he heard his voyce in the garden, hee preſently ſought a buſh to hide his head, thinking to flie from him, from whom no man can flie, but by flying vnto him. So likewiſe all of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, being partakers of their fathers impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, haue ſhunned the fight of God, as the Executioner of their eternall miſery. The Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites had rather beene encountered by an hoſte of the Philiſtines, by whom they were in no other likely-hood, but to be vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, then to come into the preſence or voyce of God, by whom oftentimes they had beene moſt mightely protected. And Sampſons wifes parents thought the ſight of God ſo fearefull and deadly a thing, that they halfe deſpaired of life, when but an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell appeered. And ſo theſe ſimple ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards were ſtroken downe amazed, when the Glory of this God began to ſhine about them. Thus ſinfull Cain ſhaketh at euery ſhadow; euery tree he thinketh a gallowes, euery one that meeteth him, he deemeth will maſſaker him: yea, euen his owne friendes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:133395:8"/> he miſtruſteth will kill him, for he knoweth that ſtuble can not ſtand before the fire, that darkeneſſe cannot continue when the light approacheth, and that man muſt needes pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, when as the God of Iuſtice is come in preſence, ſeeing man is as ſtuble, and God a conſuming fire, ſeeing man is Darkeneſſe, and God is a Light, ſeeing man is wicked, &amp; God is righteous. <hi>Timuerunt ergo timore mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no.</hi> They feared therefore (ſaith Luke) with a great feare, their ſinnes were the cauſe of their feare, and ours deſeruing no leſſe then theirs, we haue no cauſe but to feare with them: but what comfort hath the Angell brought with him? marry this. <hi>Feare not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As though he ſhould haue ſaid, yee ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull and ſinfull ſhepheards, who by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of your manifold ſins and iniquities, are aſhamed like the penſiue Publican to caſt vp your polluted eyes vnto the vnſpotted throne of the righteous God, but go mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning like reiected Cains, and curſing with Iob, the dayes of your Natiuitie, becauſe yee lie ſubiect vnto the horrible curſe of Lucifer and his Angells, by reaſon of your originall and actuall ſinnes, and therefore feare leſt God ſhould cauſe the earth to ſwallow you vp, as it did Corah and his confederates, or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:133395:8"/> elſe to be conſumed with fire, by reaſon of this fiery Light that ſhineth about you, as the Sodomites were in the dayes of Lot. If ye knew for what cauſe I am come downe vnto you, ye would be ſo farre from feare or ſorrow, that you would rather with that <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrites</hi> paſſe ouer your dayes in perpetuall Laughter. For behold I bring you Tidings, and Tidings of ſo great Ioy, that the very mountaines, if they could heare it, would skip like Rams, and the little hills like young ſheepe: ſo that henceforward you may ſing Salomons ſong, as heretofore ye haue ſighed out leremies Lamentations, wherfore looke vp and behold; behold the Angell of God who am ſent from the Throne of his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Maieſty, with all the reſt of theſe heauenly Souldiers, to declare tidings of ioy vnto you; wherefore ſeeing that you are in ſuch fauor with the King of Kings, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Iehouah, the Lord of hoſtes, in that he hath regarded you more then all the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the earth, in that you ſhall ſee the Redeemer of mankinde, euen Ieſus Chriſt the Son of God before any elſe. Seeing. (I ſay) you are in ſuch fauor, and ſo regarded of him, who is onely to be feared, there is no cauſe that ye ought to feare.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:133395:9"/>
            <p> But here by the way wee muſt note what Feare is meant in this place: for a Diuiſion muſt needs be granted, els there wil be found an Oppoſition in Religion, which Religion denieth, and a concordance of repugnant contrarieties in one ſubiect, which Reaſon in no ſort admitteth. For Feare is called <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium ſapientiae,</hi> the beginning of wiſedome, and Salomon ſaith, it is the root of Life, the fulnes of knowledge, the glory and renowne of a Chriſtian, and the moſt happy gift. And Dauid ſaith, that the Lord hath prouided an euerlaſting heritage for them that feare him: and yet it is ſaid here, Feare not. S. Paul in the eight to the Romanes ſetteth downe two kindes of feare, the one a Seruill feare, proper vnto the diuells and his damnable adherents, the other a filiall feare, or the feare of children towards their parents, which is peculiar vnto the Seruants of God. A ſeruil feare may be ſeene in Pharao, who feared the Lord when he let the people of Iſraell depart; but it was onely for feare leſt hee ſhould be deſtroied by thoſe plags &amp; puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which were denounced againſt him, &amp; which he had begun already to haue taſted of: So Cain feared when he had ſlaine his brother, ſo Iudas feared when hee had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:133395:9"/> his maiſter. Thus the Gentiles feared their Idols; for it was not for any Loue that they could beare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being ſo wicked &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly as they were; but only leſt they ſhold be hurt by them, if they did not ſerue them. Of this feare Saint Peter ſpeaking ſaith <hi>Timorem eorum ne timueritis, Feare not their feare, or feare not after their maner of fearing.</hi> meaning the ſeruil feare of wicked men. But of the other kinde of feare he ſaith preſently after <hi>Dominum autem Christum ſanctificate in Cordibus vestris cum modestia et timore.</hi> But ſanctifie the Lord Ieſus in your harts with modeſty and feare. And S. Paul writing of this feare ſaith, <hi>Cum timore &amp; tremore veſtrum &amp;c.</hi> worke out your ſaluation with modeſty and feare. And this feare is called the feare of children, which feare their Parents, more for diſpleaſing them, or prouoking their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, then for the puniſhment, which by the offence might redownd vnto themſelues. This feare was neither forbidden the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards. nor vs, nor any elſe, but onely that ſeruil feare, which the Law did bring with it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing but plagues &amp; puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was denounced againſt them that did not what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer by the Lawe was commaunded vnto them. Therefore many of the Iewes did ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilely
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:133395:10"/> feare God, but they loued him not, as may appeare, in that they had rather haue worſhipped any ſtock or ſtone if thei might haue had their choiſe without feare of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. But now, ſeeing Chriſt is come to fulfill the Law for vs, and that God; doth require nothing but our endeuoure, if with firme faith we cleaue vnto the merrits, and ſuffrings of his ſonne, therfore in this reſpect it is ſaid vnto the Shepheards, &amp; in them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, <hi>Feare not.</hi> And thus much of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, now of the reaſon therof why we need not feare.</p>
            <q>For beholde, I bring you Tidings, of Great Ioy which ſhall be vnto all people.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Non oportet eſſe tristitiae locum vbi est natalis gaudiorum:</hi> There ought not to be any place for feare or care ſaith Auguſtine, when the Birthday of Ioy &amp; bliſſe is come in preſence; <hi>for can the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Bridechamber moorne when the bridegroome is with them?</hi> haue the thunderclaps of Sinai bin able to deiect vs, &amp; ſhall not the ſongs of Sion be as forcible to erect vs? ſhall the Law terrifie vs, when the Goſpel is ſent to cheere vs? But what is this that he ſaieth, that this Ioy ſhall be vnto
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:133395:10"/> all people? ſhall all be ſaued? ſhall there be no loſt ſheep in the houſe of Iſrael? no goats to ſtand on the left hand in the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? ſhall all be carried into Abrahams boſome? ſhall all be voide of feare by his comming? I anſwer, the Lord knoweth who are his: And hath tould vs, that as the way of Life is narrowe and the gate ſtraight, ſo there ſhalbe but few that ſhall find it. For many ſaith he ſhal cry, Lord, Lord, open to vs, and ſhalbe ſent away with <hi>Neſcio vos,</hi> I know you not; And in his prayers Chriſt ſaith of himſelfe that he prayed not for all the world, but onely for thoſe that his father had giuen him out of the world. Therfore it is manifeſt, that although the Angel ſaith, that this Ioie of his Birth ſhould be vnto all, yet that all ſhall not be made Pertakers of the fruits therof. But as touching the merrits of Chriſt we muſt ſpeake after two ſorts; either according to Sufficiencie; or as touching Efficiencie. Chriſt his Death was ſufficient to haue ſaued all, but it was not efficient vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any, but onely vnto thoſe that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in him, which were not borne of water and bloud, but of the ſpirit of God. And ſo, by all, we may vnderſtand the kinds of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as a learned father ſaith, <hi>Non pro ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:133395:11"/> 
               <hi>generum, ſed pro generibus ſingulorum, &amp;c.</hi> Chriſt died not for all, of euery kinde, but for the kinde of all; euen for thoſe that were of his Church, and beleeued in him. And in this reſpect ſaith Auguſtine, let euery one wipe his teares from his eyes, and banniſh feares from his heart, that doth beeleeue in this Sauiour that is ſent. Art thou a ſinner (ſaith he) Reioyce now, becauſe a pardon is ſent from the Iudge vnto thee. Art thou a Gentill, Reioice now: becauſe thou ſhalt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſaluation with the Iewes, haſt thou bin a ſtranger from God, and an Aliant from his couenant? be glad now becauſe thou mayeſt be ingrafted into his Body. And in an other place he ſaith, Reioyce ye Iuſt, becauſe it is the Birthday of your Iuſtifier: Reioyce ye feeble and ſicke, becauſe it is the Birthday of your ſpirituall Phiſition: Reioyce ye that liue in captiuity, becauſe it is the Birthday of your Deliuerer: Reioyce ye ſeruants, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the Birthday of your Lord: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce ye freemen in heauen, becauſe it is the Birthday of him that did ſet you free: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce all Chriſtians, becauſe it is the Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day of Chriſt: and to be ſhort, Reioyce all people, becauſe it is the Birthday of the Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of all people. If any man haue cauſe to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:133395:11"/> feare or be ſorrowfull ſtill, this is the cauſe; that though Light came into the world, yet he loued Darkneſſe more then the Light, becauſe his works ſhould be euill. And thus much of the reaſon of the comfort why they ſhould not feare: now to the Tidings of Ioy it ſelfe.</p>
            <q>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you is borne this day in the Citty of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid a Sauiour, which is Christ the Lord.]</q>
            <p>Wherein wee will note, firſt the Perſon who was borne: Secondly, the Perſon of whom he was borne: Thirdly, when: Fourthly, where: and Fiftly, for what cauſe he was borne.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of this Treatiſe, you heard, in part, of the miſery of Adam after his fall, that whereas he had bin placed in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, a garden of pleaſure, inioying the ſight and preſence of God, his ſtate was compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable euen to the Angels of Heauen: for though he were ſubiect vnto God his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, yet was he Soueraigne ouer all his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, his labour was reſt, and his reſt might haue bin continuall: his paine was pleaſure, and his pleaſure might haue bin eternall; he had health without danger of ſickneſſe, and life without feare of death, the fleſh and the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:133395:12"/> ſpirit neuer ſtriued, the body obeyed the ſoule; and the ſoule gouerned the body: In a word, neither hell nor graue, death nor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, could ſo much as touch or trouble him, ſo ſtanding as God had appointed. But when he preſumed to taſte of that fruite that onely was forbidden him, preſently the caſe was cleane altered, ſo that in ſtead of life, he heard that fearefull ſentence: <hi>Thou ſhalt die the Death.</hi> Then was the Earth accurſed for his ſake, and he was thruſt out of Paradiſe, in the entrance whereof, God ſet the Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines with the blade of a ſword ſhaking, to keepe the way of the tree of life: ſo that he was faine to betake himſelfe to this miſerable and wretched world, the kingdome of the Serpent: whither could he now goe, but he ſhould meete with a curſe, ſeeing all things were accurſed? What might he do, but lie ſweating in the miſerable and pittifull pangs of deſperation? What comfort might hee finde in his wife, or his wife in him, but teares and torments, ſorrowes and ſighes, crying and howling, weeping and wailing, groaning and gnaſhing of teeth? Beeing ſo clogged with the intollerable burden of their ſinnes, ſo ouerwhelmed with the bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy floudes of Gods vengeance, ſo pittifully
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:133395:12"/> and plentifully powred out vpon them: now they perceiue the wages of their ſinne to be death and damnation: now they pine away for hunger, and would be glad of the worſt and ſowreſt apple in all Paradiſe: now they thirſt like the Hart after the water of thoſe ſweet running Riuers: now they feele the want of Gods preſence and amiable coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, they perceiue the Serpent to be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie about their heeles, moſt greedily ſucking their blood, neither can they both finde out the meanes to ſhake him off, or bruiſe his head: therefore they ſit like two children ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing by misfortune ſlaine their deere and louing father, weeping and howling the one to the other: they had ſlaine the Image of their heauenly father, they had poiſoned their ſoules with an Apple which the vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſerpent had ſpit vpon: they feele the worme of a guilty conſcience lie gnawing their bowells, and all Creatures diſobeyed them, and rebelled againſt them, in that they had ſhewed themſelues diſobedient rebells againſt their Lord and Creator. But what followed? The mercifull and louing Lord, when we ſtood at this point, and in a maner at defiance with him; although he ſaw that the imaginations of mans heart would be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:133395:13"/> and that he would alwayes beare a ſtiffe ſtomacke againſt him and his holy will; yet did he not vtterly caſt vs off, but bleſſed, O bleſſed be his name therefore, hee hath ſhewne vs a glad and cheerefull counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, it greeued him that we had deſerued his wrath, but it would haue greeued him much more, if that we had died the deſerued death: therefore that Iuſtice might haue his courſe, and his mercy neuertheleſſe might be ſeene ouer all his workes, he was content to ſend the Diadem of his deitie, that precious pearle, his owne glory, in whom was all his delight, his onely begotten, his beſt beloued Sonne, euen him before whom the 24. Elders threwe downe their Crownes humbly: whom the Angels magnified, and all the hoaſt of heauen worſhipped conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually: and to this end, that he might bee borne of ſinfull fleſh, that it being defiled with ſinne, might be cleanſed by the ſeede of righteouſneſſe; to be hungry for materiall bread; that our hungry ſoules might be fed with the bread of life: to be polluted with our ſpitle, that we might be cleanſed by his ſpirit to be condemned to death by vs, that we might attaine vnto life by him, to bee crowned with a crowne of thornes, that we
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:133395:13"/> might be crowned with crownes of glory, to ſuſtaine our ſorrowes that we might attaine his ioyes: and in a word, to be borne in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to liue in beggery, and to die with ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: for his cradle was a cratch, his life croſſed, and his kind of death accurſed, that mankind might be bleſſed: but of this hereafter.</p>
            <p>The perſon of whom he was born is moſt diſtinctly expreſſed, and expreſly deſigned in Luke, both with the name of hir eſpouſed Husband, the Citty ſhe dwelt in; the linage and Tribe ſhe came of, and the meſſenger that was ſent from god vnto hir. All which I thinke was not ſuperuacaniouſly, or in vaine ſet downe, ſeeing that neither a leafe from the tree, nor an haire can fal to the ground with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the will and prouidence of God. There is not a Letter or ſillable in the Goſpell, but hath ſome ſpecial vſe, and alſo is repleniſhed with celeſtiall and heauenly ſweetneſſe, if it haue a dilligent examiner, that can tell how <hi>to ſucke Hony out of the Rocke, and Oile out of the Flint ſtone,</hi> as the prophet ſpeaketh Eſay. 45. <hi>The Angell Gabriell was ſent to a virgin eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſed to a man, whoſe name was Ioſeph.</hi> Luke 1. &amp;c. But what virgin was it that was ſo vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, as to bee ſaluted of an Angell, and yet ſo humble as to be eſpouſed to Ioſeph a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter?
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:133395:14"/> O moſt excellent no doubt was the commixtion of virginity and humillity; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth that perſon ſmally delight God, in whome Humility commendeth Virginity, and Virginity exorneth, and beautifieth hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility. Wee heare ſhe was a Virgin, and and we heare ſhe was humble; if we can not imitate the virginity of this humble woman, yet let vs folow the Humility of that Virgin. Commendable is Virginity, but more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary is Humillity: for that is but Counſelled. but this is commaunded: that we are inuited vnto, but vnto this we are compelled. Of that it is ſaid, I would that euery one were a virgine as my ſelfe; but of this it is affirmed, That except we be as humble as little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren we cannot enter Heauen. For without Virginity a man may be ſaued, but without Humillity hee can not. And therefore ſaith Mary in her ſong of thankſgiuing. He reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted (what? not my Virginity) but the Lowly eſtate of his handmaid. Of this hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble virgin came Chriſt in his humility, &amp; for this he reſpected hir, to ſhew vs how he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecteth the humble. It was meet that ſhee ſhould be meek and Humble: of whom the meeke and humble in hart ſhould proceed; &amp; it was requiſite that ſhe ſhould be a pure
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:133395:14"/> Virgin &amp; vnſpoted, of whom the Immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late &amp; vnſpotted Sauior ſhould be born, that ſhould clenſe the ſpots of the impure world. Adam and Eue as they were the begetters of all, ſo were they the deſtroiers of all; yea and which is a more miſchiefe, they firſt deſtroid vs before they begat vs; for their Seed being impure by their ſinne we were al conceaued ſinfull, and ſubiect vnto deſtruction; The conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whereof might cauſe vs to feare with the Shepheards; But ſaith the Angell, <hi>Feare not,</hi> for ye haue wherewith to redeeme the Impurity of your conception: euen the purity of the conception of your Redeemer. If he had bin vncleane himſelfe in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, how could he haue clenſed ours; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to make them cleane which were borne of vncleane ſeed he was conceiued without any ſeed of man. For (as the Angell Gabriell tould hir) the Holy Ghoſt came vpon hir, &amp; the power of the moſt High ouerſhadowed hir. And therefore that holy thing that was borne of hir, was, &amp; is called the ſon of God: what greater miracle then this? yea who euer heard ſo great miracles as theſe, as that God ſhould be man and yet God ſtil? That a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin ſhould be a mother without the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hir Virginity? Surely I may now with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:133395:15"/> ſecurity expect, that that holy one ſhall not ſee corruption, but ſhall riſe againe for our Iuſtification, ſeing he would not ſuffer cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in the Virginity of his mother.</p>
            <p>Further, we may obſerue this in the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, how he maketh the woman a Conduite Pipe of our comfort and Felicity, which before was the inſtrument of our care and miſery; ſo that as before we laid the fault vpon Eua, Saying, The woman which thou gaueſt me, gaue to me to eate, &amp;c. So now we may with ioiful harts ſay to God; <hi>Mary</hi> which thou gaueſt me, gaue me of the Tree of Life, &amp; I did eate of it. And it was ſweeter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hony vnto my mouth, for in it thou haſt reuiued me: Thus the wiſe woman rebuil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the houſe, which the fooliſh had caſt downe before. Mary, like the tree of life, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the fruite of Saluation for vs, as Eue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the apple of Damnation vnto vs.</p>
            <p>Nowe let vs proceede to the time of his birth, which was in the midſt of winter, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of the colde and tempeſtuous winter, when all thinges ſeeme dead and withered, when the Trees, not onely beare no fruite, but alſo, want their Leaues: when the birdes ſing not, nor the Sunne warmeth, nor the heauens are cleere, nor the Aire tollerable,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:133395:15"/> nor the Earth delightfull, nor any creature cheerefull, euen in this withered, barren, and frozen time of the yeare; nay of the world: yea in the dark night of this winter was our Sauiour Borne: for then was the night of which the Apoſtle ſpeaking ſaith now is paſt, when darkenes was ouer the face of the deepe, yea a ſpirituall and inward darkeneſſe of the minde when the Light of Knowledge and Vnderſtanding was very much obſeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, &amp; the darkenes of ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce had poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed mens harts, that few had the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, or could be inſtructed in the path of his wayes. There was no Prophet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, no chirping of birds was heard in their Land, there was a barrennes, not onely of good workes, but euen of the leaues of good words. Theeues made their dennes in the Temple, and Foxes crept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sion. Charity was cold, and mens hearts were frozen: Iuſtice was baniſhed, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſnes embraced: and therefore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the time of the yeare, I meane the courſe of their life, the ſtormes and tempeſts of Gods heauy iudgments, might with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be exſpected. But euen in this cod dead winter, and darke time of the night, warme and cheerefull Light appeered vnto the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:133395:16"/> Shepheards, and the glory of the Lord did ſhine moſt brightly vpon them, and the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of this ioyfull Natiuity was tould vnto them, which is all one with that which the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith. That when we were Sinners Chriſt died for vs. And this was the fulneſſe of time. Gal. 4. for the fulneſſe of Earthly and temporal things, had made a dearth and barrenneſſe of heauenly and ſpiritual. This was the time which the Prophet Ioell pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of, <hi>when the mountaines ſhould drop downe new wine, and the hils ſhould flow with milke, and all the Riuers of Iudah ſhould flowe with waters.</hi> This was the day wherein God promiſed <hi>the Heauens ſhould ſend downe their Dew, and the Cloudes drop Righteouſneſſe, and Saluation and Iuſtice ſhould growe foorth of the Earth together.</hi> This was the day <hi>which many Kinges and Prophets deſired to ſee, and could not ſee it:</hi> Yea happy were they that were ſo happy as to hope for this day: Father Sime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on deſired to liue to this day, though hee liued not a day longer, and therefore as ſoone as euer he ſaw him whom his ſoule had ſo long longed after, preſently he ſaid, <hi>Lord now lettest thou thy ſeruant depart in peace, for myne eyes haue ſeene thy ſaluation. &amp;c.</hi> This was the comfortable day, in the hope wherof
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:133395:16"/> the Prophets comforted vp themſelues and the people, declaring it in ſuch ſort, as though the inſenſible creatures, as the mountaines and the vallies ſhould be refreſhed thereby: Such was the propheſie of Eſay: <hi>Reioyce, O heauens, and be glad O earth, burſt foorth into prayſes O mountaines, for God hath viſited his people, and will haue mercy on his afflicted.</hi> And the Prophet Zacharie ſaith: <hi>Reioyce, for great ioy O daughter Sion, ſhout out for ioy O daughter Ieruſalem, Behold thy king commeth vnto thee.</hi> If theſe reioiced ſo much in that the Meſſias ſhould come, How much more ſhould our ſoules magnifie the Lord, and our ſpirits re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in him, who already is come, and as this day born vnto vs? This is the day which the Lord did promiſe to our forefathers, let vs reioyce and be glad in it. Let vs clap our handes for ioy and gladnes, let vs ſing vnto the Lord with the voyce of melodie: for Chriſt our Sauiour is borne as this day, let vs ſing prayſes therefore all of vs with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: But ſome man wil ſay, this day was long agoe, it is olde and ſtale newes that Chriſt was borne, I know indeede that the Meſſias was borne, not onely long before our times, but euen before all times. But I reade alſo, that Ieſus is yeſterday, and to day,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:133395:17"/> and the ſame for euer: and therefore if the fathers reioiced to ſee his day before it came, we may as well celebrate the memoriall of it as preſent now it is come.</p>
            <p>But now let vs proceede and inquire out the place of his birth: And that the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts affirme to be Bethlehem the citie of Dauid, what if it be a poore village? what if it be the leaſt in all the land of Iudea? ſhall it be an argument that he was not born there? nothing leſſe, for what was more beſeeming him, that when he was rich, became poore for vs: and of a great and mightie Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a little child, then to be born in a poore and little village. And in this he declareth vnto vs, how greatly he affecteth the poore in ſpirite, and thoſe that are of a lowly and humble hart: For as he ſayd vnto his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of his waſhing of their feete, ſo it may be ſaid of his other actions, I haue giuen you an example, that you ſhould doe as I haue done: And in this ſhall all men knowe that ye are my Diſciples. If thou wouldſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh betwixt the corne and the chaffe, caſt them foorth; the good corne deſcendeth, but the chaffe will aſcend: the wicked are ſtill aſpiring, and mounting vpward in this world, but the godly caſt down their crowns
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:133395:17"/> with the 24. Elders at the feete of the Lamb: <hi>Dicit ſe filius indignum vt, pater eum iudicet dignum;</hi> The prodigall ſonne termeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnworthy, that his father might terme him worthy: for it is alwayes true, that <hi>Cum inclinatur humilitas, excitatur miſerecordia,</hi> when humilitie ſtoupeth downe, mercy ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vp. And therefore ſaith Peter: <hi>Humiſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini ſub potenti manu domini, vt vos exaltat in diem Iudicij,</hi> Humble your ſelues vnder the mightie hand of God, that he may exalt you in the day of iudgement: The tree doth not grow vpward except it firſt take root down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde: The higher wee meane to builde an houſe, the lower we muſt lay the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for he that thinketh to doe the one, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out performing the other, may ſeeme frugall in the beginning, but will prooue a foole in the ende: The high hils ſeeme next vnto the cloudes, but the lowe vallies are moſt refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by them, euen ſo God reſiſteth the proude, but giueth grace vnto the humble: The glow-worme ſhineth bright, and in the darke gloriouſly, but is blacke and vgly when it commeth to light: whatſoeuer the condition of the proude man ſeemeth now in the darknes of this worlde, I am ſure that when the Sonne of righteouſnes ſhall ſhine
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:133395:18"/> in the laſt day it ſhall prooue very lowe and baſe.</p>
            <p>I would that ye were all little Bethelem of Iuda, poore in ſpirit, and little in your owne eyes, that Chriſt might vouchſafe to bee borne in you by his ſpirit, as he was there in the fleſh. Bethelem ſignifieth as much as the houſe of bread, therefore it is good to bee there: and if we may not build Tabernacles of abode in that place, yet let vs ſend thither with Iacob, our Camels and Aſſes, I meane our affections, that we may liue, and not die: It is the houſe of bread, euen of that liuing bread that came downe from heauen, of which whoſoeuer eateth ſhall liue for euer. Happy were the people that were in ſuch a caſe, yea bleſſed was Bethelem that had the Lord for their bread. Let vs pray, beloued, that we may be alſo Bethelem, the houſe of bread, that the Lord may turne in vnto vs; for otherwiſe, if we be vnprouided, as he that was faine to trouble his neighbour at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night for a fewe loaues, we are not fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſo great a gueſt. But who hath this Bread? euen he whoſe heart is confirmed &amp; ſtrengthned, for bread ſtrengthneth the hart of man; and who is confirmed or ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in hart? but he whoſe hart is ſetled to the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:133395:18"/> Commandements of the Lord, which doth not wauer in his faith, but goeth forward with a determined hart towards the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Canaan, forgetting the fleſh pots of Egypt which are behinde, and not ſo much as loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king backe towards the forſaken Sodom. For if any one be doubtfull and wauering in his faith, if a man be not reſolued to proceed in his vocation, but is in a quandary, whither he ſhould go forward or backeward, deny his faith, or maintaine it, forſake his ſinnes, or returne to his vomit: this man is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to receiue the Lord: Chriſt will not be borne in ſuch a mans houſe who wanteth faith the bread of life, as the Scripture calleth it, ſaying, the iuſt ſhal liue by faith. But what! did Bethelem beleeue in Chriſt? did ſhee ſo abound with the bread of faith, that the Lord choſe his Inne there, rather then any where elſe? nay ſurely, ſhe was farre from that in nature, which ſhe ſeemed to be by hir name, though ſhe brought forth this Sonne, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the duty of a mother, yet ſhe was farre from a motherlike affection towards him: though the walles of hir houſe contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him carnally, yet the affections of hir hart would not entertaine him ſpiritually. And indeed, we may ſay of this as Paul doth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:133395:19"/> of other like myſteries: All things were done in former times, in tipes and figures. The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing ſoule is that true citty of bread where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Chriſt is dayly borne ſpiritually, as he was in Bethelem carnally: So that I thinke this name was giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hir, rather as a propheſie that the bread of Life, Chriſt Ieſus ſhould be borne in hir, then for that ſhee was fed or nouriſhed by him.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, the holy ghoſt not onely hath expreſſed the name of the towne, but alſo the very houſe, yea, and the very place or roome of the houſe wherein he was borne, neither is it to be thought curioſity in vs to ſearch the meaning of euery particular, which the ſpirit of wiſedome ſo curiouſly hath expreſſed. <hi>Sub ſordido palliolo lateat ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia.</hi> Vnder a patched coate may lurke wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and vnder a plaine ſtile, may myſtical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be contained moſt learned inſtitutions; ſo that, not onely the deep Ocean ſea is to bee ſounded, but alſo the ſhallow foords of Meander are diligently to be conſidered. Neither do I thinke it haphazard that Chriſt was borne in a ſtable (for ſuch is the place that the Euangeliſts affirme that he was born in) but that it was appointed by God for ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall reaſons long before, who doth nothing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:133395:19"/> raſhly, but hath a reaſon of all his actions.</p>
            <p>Ye heard before how honorable was the condition of Adam in his Innocencie, being like vnto God, and created in his Image; But the Pſalmiſt witneſſeth, man being in honor, and wanting vnderſtanding, he was compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto the Beaſts that periſh, and in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural affections became indeed a very beaſt, and for his beaſtly ſimilitude and reſembla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſtood tied as it were at the manger, to receiue the fodder of beaſts. A ſtrange alteration (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) that he that was the poſſeſſor of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, the lord of the whole earth, the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the god of ſaboth, the brother of the bleſſed and celeſtiall ſpirits, and the perfect Image of the holy Trinity, ſhould ſo degenerate from his kinde, as to become ſo lowe and baſe as a Beaſt. But marke heere, and conſider the proceedings of god: for whereas man being become a beaſt had left the Heauenly bread of Life, delighting more in the fodder of Beaſtes; Behold now that bread of Life is turned into Fleſh, nay into graſſe, which is the food of Beaſts (for all fleſh is graſſe) and lieth in a racke or manger to be eaten and chewed of vs beaſts. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let the Oxe now know his own, and the Aſſe his maſters crib. Let them drawe neere
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:133395:20"/> to him in the ſtable, whom they fled from in the garden. Let them honor him in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, whom they contemned in his maieſty, and let them feede on him beeing graſſe, whom they loathed when he was bread; yea let them with an eager and liuely faith rumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and chew vpon him, that they may be nouriſhed and grow vp by him. He muſt be receiued by Hearing, chewed by Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and diſieſted by beleeuing, or as an other ſaith. The eating of his fleſh, is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine hunger and deſire, to be incorporated into him. And indeed as our ſauiour ſayth. He that eateth the fleſh of the ſonne of man &amp;c. ſhall liue for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Sauiour]</hi> But wherefore did Chriſt ſo debaſe himſelfe? Euen that he might be a Sauior vnto vs? that he might drawe vs vnto him with the ropes of man, and with the cords of his loue, as Oſe ſpeaketh. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he leaueth no meanes vntried, to bring vs vnto him, no not though they be neuer ſo baſe, as to be borne in a Stable.</p>
            <p>There is none of vs that liue in this regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of death, in the infirmities of the fleſh, and amidſt the Temptations that are commonly offered, but hath need of Counſell, of Help,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:133395:20"/> and of comfort, for we are <hi>Faciles ad ſeducen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, debiles ad operandum, &amp; fragiles ad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtendum:</hi> if we would diſcerne betwixt good and euill, we are eaſily deceiued. If we trie to do good, we are quickly tyred. And if we are tempted, we are ſudenly ſubdued. Therfore to enlighten our blindnes, to help our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and to defend our frailneſſe, Chriſt was borne vnto vs. Therefore <hi>Feare not.</hi> For if he be in vs, who ſhall deceiue vs? If hee bee with vs, what can we not do in him that ſtrengthneth vs? If he ſtand for vs, what need we care who be againſt vs? ſeeing he is the <hi>faithful Counſeller,</hi> which can neither deceiue nor be deceiued, ſeeing he is the <hi>Almightie God;</hi> which is neuer wearied; ſeeing he is <hi>the ſtrong man,</hi> that bindeth Sathan, breaketh the Serpents Head, and is neuer vanquiſhed. Wherefore <hi>Feare not,</hi> O Adam, neither flie any longer. Runne not in to the buſhes from the ſight of thy Maker, for behold, hee hath ſent thee this day a Sauiour. Once thou waſt perſuaded by the ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to ſin againſt God, and being taken in the fact, thou hadſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to feare. Yea perhaps he brandiſhed his fiery ſword againſt thee: but now it is not ſo. He commeth not with weapons, to puniſh, but with mercy, to preſerue. If thou ſaiſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:133395:21"/> thou heardſt his voice, and therefore fledſt; why? he is an Infant, and without any voyce, and if he haue a voyce, it is a voyce more to be pitied then feared. Yea in this thou ſhalt know, that he is come to ſaue thee, and not deſtroy thee, in that he fighteth for thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch as roſe againſt thee. Thou hadſt but two enemies, Sinne and Death, the death of the body, and the death of the ſoule: hee commeth to deſtroy either, and to ſaue thee from both: therefore feare not, he deſtroyed ſinne in his owne perſon, when hee tooke mans fleſh vpon him without any pollution: For great was the violence that was offered vnto ſinne, when humane nature, which was alwayes before as it were in a leproſie, was found in Chriſt as white as ſnowe: therefore I hope, yea I am aſſured that he can plucke out the beame in mine eye, which hath neuer a moate in his owne, that he may ſatisfie for my ſinne, which was neuer defiled himſelfe with any. I reade of two that were called Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that is, Sauiour, who as they went before this that we ſpeake of, ſo I thinke they were tipes and prefigurations of him. One of which brought the people out of Babilon, the other brought them into Canaan, both defended them from their enemies, but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:133395:21"/> ſaued them from their ſinnes: But this deliuereth vs from our ſinnes, bringeth vs out of bondage, and placeth vs as kings in the land of the liuing. Sinne had made a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of the bodie from the ſoule, and the ſoule from the bodie, &amp; of both from God: but Ieſus hath brought them all together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, yea &amp; in a far neerer coniunction then euer before. For now they that were at mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual variance, are now reconciled frends. Yea and ſo reconciled, that as in the bleſſed Deity there is a trinitie in perſons, but an vnitie in ſubſtance: Euen ſo in this happy reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation there is a Trinitie in ſubſtance, but an Vnitie in the perſons. And as there the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie of perſons doth not breake the vnity, nor the ſimplicitie of the vnitie doth not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the trinitie: So heere in like manner the perſons doth not confound the ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nor the ſubſtances doe hinder the vnitie of the perſon; for the word, the Soule, and fleſh, are become one perſon, and theſe three are one, and this one thing is three, not by confuſion of the ſubſtances, but by the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the perſon: O wonderfull and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excellent vnion! who euer heard that things ſo diuerſe ſhould ſo meete together, as to be one perſon; yea, ſoone perſon, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:133395:22"/> God may be ſayde to haue done in the body, the body may be ſayd to haue done it. And whatſoeuer the body ſuffereth, God may be ſayd to haue ſuffred, by reaſon of this coniunction. The Angels ſurely were aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied heere at, ſeeing him beneath themſelues, whom they did alwayes adore and worſhip aboue themſelues. The Cherubins which God commaunded to be placed at the two ends of the Arke of the couenant, with their face being turned one towardes another, and both looking on the mercyſeate, do ſignifie as much vnto vs, as that they admyred and wondered to ſee a woorke of ſo great pietie. <hi>viz.</hi> To ſee God made the propitiatory ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the worlde, and to debaſe himſelfe ſo low as to become a man But behold the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie (as I may terme it) of Adam fulfilled, Man (quoth he) ſhall leaue father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and cleaue vnto his wife, and they two ſhall be one fleſhe. Chriſt Ieſus leaueth his Father and the Angelles in Heauen, for to aſſociate himſelfe vnto his ſpouſe in earth, and (as you haue heard) ſhe is bone of his bone; and fleſh of his fleſh, for they are no more two but one perſon. And this beloued, is tydings of great ioy; for now, according to the lawes of wedlocke, we may aſſure our
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:133395:22"/> ſelues to haue all thinges in common with him; ſo that he ſhall take vpon him our ſins and tranſgreſſions as his owne, and we again ſhall be partakers of his puritie and holineſſe as our owne; That our debts ſhall be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at his hands, and we be ſaued harmles &amp; diſcharged of them, which is all one with that which is ſayd here; that a Sauiour is born vnto vs. But this by the way, wee muſt not now forget, that it is our partes and duties to forget likewiſe our owne people and fathers houſe; to abandon all ſtrange loues, and to admit none into the fellowſhip of that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall bedde, but to cleaue onely vnto him, to honor and obey him, to reuerence and loue him, to keepe our chaſtities vnſpotted, our ſoules and bodies pure and vndefiled for him: And as our nature is one with his who ſo is heauenly and diuine; ſo to liue an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly &amp; diuine life, neither louing any thing that he lotheth, or lothing any thing that he loueth, but that his will be our will, and his precepts our continuall practiſes.</p>
            <p>As he hath ouercome Sinne in his owne perſon, in being conceiued, and liuing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Sinne, ſo hath he deliuered vs alſo from the guilt therof, by ſuffering the puniſhment for vs, and imputing his Righteouſnes vnto
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:133395:23"/> vs: alſo in that he ouercame Sin, it appeareth plainely that he hath vanquiſhed death. For death is but the ſtipend and wages of Sinne, and as it were the effect and fruite of Sinne. For if man had auoyded the firſt, he ſhould ſurely haue eſcaped the latter, for it was not the corruption of our bodies that made our ſoules ſinfull, but the Sinne of our Soules that made our bodies corruptible. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the fountaine be drie, the brookes muſt needs be drie: If the cauſe be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, the effects muſt of neceſſity follow, as if the Sunne be darke, the Moone and the Starres can giue no light: death a great while amazed al mankind. (I ſpeake of the eternall and neuer-dying death, of which Gregory ſpeaking faith <hi>Mors erit immortalis, defectus indeficiens, &amp; finis infinitus,</hi> vnto which belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the worm that neuer dieth, when a man ſhall be alwayes dying and neuer dead euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly, hauing an end, and yet no end; ſtil decaying, and neuer decayed. Becauſe his end euer beginneth, his death euer liueth, and his decay neuer ceaſeth, From which, by the Law, there was no Redemption, which would haue brought into eternall ſubiection all creatures whatſoeuer, if this Sauiour and deliuerer had not bin born vnto vs, ſo that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:133395:23"/> ſoule like the mothers in Rama<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, might haue iuſtly ſighed forth thoſe dolefull dirges of weeping, mourning, and lamentation; and with Iob haue curſed the dayes of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity, by reaſon of the torments and tortures of the dead. But as the Aſſe called <hi>Cumanus aſmus,</hi> getting vp and downe in a Lions skin, did for a while terrifie his maiſter, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward being deſcried, did do him no good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: So death which ſometimes made afraid the wiſemen of the world, by his skin or ſting of Eternity. Nowe ſince our Sauiour hath bereaued him thereof, ſeemeth contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, euen vnto Children, ſo that they dare boldly goe vnto it, for they know it ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifite them very much: for if they be oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with any miſeries or calamities in this life, when they ſhall come to death, they ſhall be diſcharged, and death as an Aſſe ſhall beare their burdens for them; yea they know, that death vnto them ſhall bee no death, but an entrance into euerlaſting life, and therefore they feare not.</p>
            <p>God is the life of the ſoule, as the Soule is of the bodie, by ſinning voluntarily the Soule loſt God hir life, therefore ſhe can not now at hir pleaſure giue life. She would not be gouerned of God, therefore now ſhe can
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:133395:24"/> not gouerne the body. Hauing not obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hir ſuperiour why ſhould ſhe command hir inferiour. God found his creature rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious againſt him. The Soule was found a tranſgreſſor of Gods law, now therefore ſhe findeth a law in hir members repugning the law of hir mind. Sinne ſeparated betwixt God and hir, therefore death doth ſeperate betwixt hir and the body. The Soule could not be diuided from God, but by ſin, neither can the body from the Soule, but by death: what iniury therfore ſuffred ſhe, if ſhe ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that of hir ſubiect which ſhe committed hir ſelf againſt hir prince? Nothing ſurely was more agreeable vnto Iuſtice, then that death ſhould be rewarded with death; ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall with corporall, and voluntary with ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. Whenas man therfore had deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued according to either nature, to ſuffer this double death, the one ſpirituall and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, the other corporall and neceſſary; from either of them the man-god Chriſt Ieſus moſt mightily hath deliuered vs, by his owne corporall and voluntary death: and in that one of his, hath ſatisfied for both of ours. If he had not died corporally, he had not paid our debt, and if he had not died vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily, his death had not bin meritorious.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:133395:24"/> But now if (as it is ſaid) the merit of death is ſinne, and the woges of ſinne is death. Chriſt remitting and forgiuing our ſinne, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ſinners, the merit is aboliſhed, &amp; the debt is diſcharged. But how ſhall we knowe that Chriſt can forgiue vs our ſinnes? euen by this, in that he is God: But how ſhall wee knowe that hee is God? his miracles doe prooue it: for he doth the works which no no man elſe can doe, yea God himſelfe from heauen hath confirmed the ſame. Therefore if Chriſt be for vs, who is againſt vs? If Ieſus iuſtifie vs, who ſhall condemne vs? It is he, and no other, to whom we confeſſe our ſins, ſaying, Againſt thee onely haue I ſinned, &amp;c. Who could better, nay who could at all forgiue vs that which was committed againſt him? Or how can he not do this, which can do all things? In a word, if I can pardon that which is committed againſt me, if I will, ſhal not God our Chriſt be able to forgiue that which is committed againſt him, if he wil? If therefore hee can forgiue and pardon our ſinnes, both becauſe hee is omnipotent, and onely can, becauſe they are onely done againſt him. Surely bleſſed is the man to whom this Lord Chriſt will not impute ſinne. Therefore we know that Chriſt, by the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:133395:25"/> power of his diuinity is able to forgiue ſins: now of his will who need to doubt? For hee that debaſed him ſelfe ſo much, as to take our fleſh vpon him, and to ſuffer death for vs, ſhall we thinke that he will not imparte vnto vs his righteouſnes? ſurely yes, ſo that as it is euident by the conſideration of his deitie, that he is able to forgiue our ſinnes: ſo it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by the conſideration of his Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that he is willing ſo to do. But what other argument haue we that he hath vanquiſhed death? marry this, becauſe hee ſuffered it which did not deſerue it. And therefore with what reaſon can that bee required of vs, which an other hath already paid for vs? hee that tooke away the merrit of ſinne, by giuing his righteouſnes vnto vs, hee hath paid the debt of death, and reſtored life vnto vs; for ſo death being vanquiſhed, life is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, as ſinne being taken away, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is returned.</p>
            <p>But how could he die which was God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Euen in this reſpect, that hee was man. But how could the death of one man ſatisfie for an other? becauſe he was Iuſt and Innocent that died. As he was a man, he might die, but being guiltleſſe, it was not neceſſary. Indeed a ſinner is not able to ſatisfie the debt of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:133395:25"/> death for an other ſinner, for euery one di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for his owne ſinne: but he that hath no cauſe to die for his owne, ſhall we not thinke his death may be a ranſome for an other? Surely by how much the more vniuſtly hee dieth which hath not deſerued death, by ſo much the more iuſtly he liueth for whom he ſo dieth. But what equity is it (ſaiſt thou) that an innocent perſon ſhould die for the guilty? I tell thee, it is not Iuſtice, but mercy: if it ſhould haue bin Iuſtice, then he had not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed voluntarily, but of duty: if of duty, then he himſelfe ſhould die indeed, yet he for whom he ſo died ſhould not liue. But neuertheleſſe if it be not Iuſtice, yet it is not againſt iuſtice, otherwiſe God could not haue bin iuſt and mercifull at once. But although one iuſt man may ſatisfie for one ſinner, yet howe is it that one may ſatisfie for many? for it might ſeeme inough, if one dying for one, do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore Life vnto one. To this the Apoſtle ſhall anſwere, As by the offence of one, the fault came on all men to the Condemnation of death: So by the Righteouſnes of one, the benefit abounded towards all men to the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of Life. For as by one mans diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience many were made Sinners: So by the Obedience of one, many are become
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:133395:26"/> Righteous. But perhaps one man might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore Righteouſnes vnto many, but Life, not ſo. By one man (ſaith he) death entered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, and ſo by one is Life regayned; For as by Adam all die, ſo by Chriſt ſhall all be made aliue. For what! ſhal one man ſinne and all become guilty, and ſhall the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of one redownd but to one only? was gods Iuſtice ſuch, as to condemne al for one, and cannot his mercy be as great, as to ſaue all by one? Or could Adam do more in euill, then Chriſt in good? Shall Adams Sin be imputed vnto me, and ſhall not Chriſtes righteouſnes belong vnto me? Shall his diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience be the cauſe of my Death, and ſhal not Chriſts obedience reſtore me to life? but thou wilt ſay, we are worthely guilty of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams Sinne, becauſe we were contained in him when he ſinned, and were begotten of his fleſh in the ſinfull Luſt of the Fleſh. But I ſay, more truly are we begotten of god ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſpirit, then of Adam accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh: I meane, if we are of the number of thoſe whom God hath predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated before the creation of the world vnto Life; And that we are begotten of god S. Iohn witneſſeth where he ſaith, Which were not begotten of blood, nor after the will of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:133395:26"/> the Fleſh, nor of Man, but of God. And in one of his Epiſtles he likewiſe maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this holy generation, ſaying. He that is borne of God ſinneth not. But thou wilt ſay, our carnall concupiſcence and ſinne, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth that we haue deſcended of ſinners ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fleſh, and not of God. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, this generation or birth is not ſeene in the fleſh, but in the ſpirit and minde: and that of thoſe onely that can ſay with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, we haue the minde of the Lord, and who haue the ſpirit, bearing witneſſe to their ſpirits, that they are the ſonnes of God: for by the ſpirit of God, chaſtitie is infuſed into our mindes, as by the fleſh which is of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, concupiſcence is diffuſed about in our members: and as that which is deſcended vnto vs from the parents of our bodies, doth neuer depart in this life from the fleſh: ſo the other proceeding from the father of our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, is neuer excident from the intention of the mindes of his children that are perfected in him. If then we are borne of God, and elected in Chriſt, what equity is it that our earthly and humane generation ſhould hurt vs more then our ſpirituall and heauenly is able to helpe vs? Can our carnall ſucceſſion hinder the election of God, and a momentary
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:133395:27"/> ſinne be a let vnto his eternall and euerlaſting purpoſe? Nay if by one man death entered vpon all, ſhall not life by one man, eſpecially ſuch a man as Chriſt, be giuen vnto all? And if in Adam wee all died, ſhall we not much more in Chriſt be made aliue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the fault was nothing ſo much as the gift; for iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment came for one ſinne vnto condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but grace was of many ſinnes vnto iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. Chriſt therefore both could remit our ſinnes, in that he was God, &amp; die, in that he was man, and by dying, deliuer vs from death, in that he was iuſt, and though but one, yet be ſufficient vnto iuſtification and life for all, becauſe both ſinne and alſo death did enter into vs all by one. Thus all of Chriſt was powerfull to helpe vs, in euery thing he was profitable for vs, neither was his infirmity leſſe auaileable then his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie; for although by the power of his deitie hee remoued the yoke of ſinne from our neckes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet in the infirmity of his fleſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the power of death by his death. And therefore true is that of the Apoſtle, the weakeneſſe of God is ſtrongeſt vnto men; for his death hath freed vs from death, as his life did from errour, and his grace from ſinne. But ſome man may ſay, if Chriſt hath thus
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:133395:27"/> deliuered vs from the power of ſinne and death, what is the reaſon that we die dayly, and are not preſently clothed with immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie? mary that the truth and verity of God may be fulfilled, for ſeeing God loueth both mercy and truth, it is neceſſary that man die becauſe God hath ſpoken it, and yet that he riſe and liue againe, becauſe God is merciful. So that death, although it doth not perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally raigne ouer vs, yet it remaineth for a time in vs for the truth of Gods ſake; euen as ſinne alſo, though it raigne not in our mortall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, yet it is not altogether aboliſhed out of vs.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as death was put to death by this Lord of life, ſo likewiſe was ſathan the prince of death: for as Origen teſtifieth there were beſides the Theeues, two crucified on the Croſſe of Chriſt. Chriſt himſelfe viſibly, with his wil, and for a time: the diuell inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly, againſt his wil, and for euer: ſo that now the band of death which was drawne together, by the ſinful life of one, was looſed by the righteous death of an other, and our malicious aduerſary that neuer ment vs good is now ouertaken in the effect of his malice: for by haſtening the Sonne of Gods execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he brought on all the ſonnes of mens
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:133395:28"/> redemption, and his owne confuſion. <hi>Ruens dum irruens, captus dum capit, mortalem perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quens, &amp; in ſaluatorem incidens.</hi> Falling whilſt following, caught whilſt catching, purſuing a creature, and lighting on the Sauiour: ſo that as before he had ouercome the firſt Adam, and in him, had held all mankinde captiue, now he is ouercome himſelfe of a ſecond A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, &amp; by his puiſſance looſeth the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an kinde that were choſen out of mankinde, and now ſet free from the ſinne of man, by this his aduerſary, that was without ſinne, though he were of mankinde. And is not this (bleſſed brethren) Tidings of great ioy, that ſuch a Sauiour is borne vnto vs, that hath ſubdued all thoſe that were any whit againſt vs? Therefore now, O dead Adam, lift vp thy head again; take hart vnto thee, and be of a good courage, for hee is borne that hath vanquiſhed thy enemies, Sin, Death, and the Diuel: that wil reconcile thee to thy creator, and make thee a newe creature: thou haſt bin dead a great while like Lazarus, and wee may thinke with Mary, that thou ſtinkeſt, but he that could make the dry bones come together, and ſtand vp, is able to raiſe thee from the duſt of death, and to ſet thee with the Princes of the liuing God. Thou haſt layne a long time in thy goare, like the woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:133395:28"/> man of Iericho, and many haue paſſed by thee, but none ſhewed compaſſion on thee; but behold, here is come a good Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritane to binde vp thy wounds, and to reſtore thee to thy health, deſpaire not. This (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) is the comfort of a Chriſtian, the ſolace of a ſinner, and the tidings of ioy that is come vnto all people: euen that there is borne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs a <hi>Sauiour.</hi> O name aboue all names, and moſt woorthy to be euer named; It is euen as honny vnto my mouth, and as marrowe vnto my bones; O bleſſed be this name of the Lord, for it turneth my water into wine, my malady into melody, my ſorrowes into ſollace, my muſing into muſicke, and my ſighing into ſinging: like oyle, it maketh me to haue a cheerefull countenance, and like bread, it ſtrengtheneth my fainting hart: it is as ſweet incenſe powred forth, and therefore ſaith Solomon, the virgins loue him. I wil not nowe be afraide for any terrours by night, nor for the arrowes that flie by day: for my Sauiour will ſaue me vnder his wings, and I ſhall be ſafe vnder his fethers, his mercy and truth ſhall be my ſhield and buckler.</p>
            <p>Many were the fauors that God ſhewed vnto the Iſraelites, in bringing them from their grieuous bondage in Egypt, to their
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:133395:29"/> ſtately gouernment in Canaan, whereof Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid ſeemeth very proud in that Pſalme that he compiled of it. But if you conſider them they will appeare nothing, in compariſon of thoſe benefits which this ſweet name Sauior doth import vnto vs. Firſt, ſaith Dauid, he deuided the red Sea, and led them ſafely through it, when their foes were drenched and ouerwhelmed in it, and in the day time he led them with a Cloud. This was their Baptiſme vnder Moſes as Paul ſaith, but if we compare it with ours, we ſhall finde that we haue drowned a greater enemie, euen the infernall Pharao the diuill of hell, as many as are baptiſed in the red Sea of this our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours bloud. Dauid goeth farther and ſaith; As he led them in the day time with a cloud, ſo did he in the night time with a light of fire. This was, I confeſſe, a token of Gods great loue, to giue them ſuch a Light; but it was nothing in compariſon of that light which ſhineth in the darkneſſe of our heartes and minds, by whch whoſoeuer walketh, ſhal neuer ſee darkneſſe, but ſhal haue the Light of Life. Furthermore he ſaith, for the glory of the Iew he claue the rock in the wildernes and gaue them Drinke as out of the great depth. But Paule ſaith for the comfort of vs Gentiles. This rock is Chriſt, which being
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:133395:29"/> clouen on the croſſe by the ſouldiers ſpeare, there guſhed out moſt plentifully that water of Life which ſerueth to ſatisfie the thirſt of euery ſoule. Dauid addeth. God opened the Doores of Heauen, and rained downe Manna vppon them to eate, which was the food of Angels: but that was but a figure of this bread of life, which is come down from Heauen vnto vs, of which whoſoeuer eateth ſhall liue for euer. Finally, Dauid reioyſeth that God by the hand of his ſeruant Ioſhua, conducted his people into Canaan, and ſet them in poſſeſſion of that good and pleaſant land. But that was but as dung in compariſon of our inheritance, our heauenly Canaan the kingdome of God, of which Ioſuah our Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus will crowne vs Kings for euer, if we fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him as he hath commanded. Seeing then (O happy Chriſtians) that Dauid ſo much reioyced for thoſe temporal bleſſings that God had beſtowed vpon his forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, how much more ought wee to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in the remembrance of thoſe ſpirituall benedictions and graces which we ſhall bee pertakers of for euer, by the comming of our Sauiour, wherein we ſeem as farre to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede the Iewes in the fauour of GOD, as the Iewes exceeded all other nations of the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:133395:30"/> world whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euen Christ the Lord]</hi> It is added more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer for the increaſe of our comforte, that our Sauiour is Chriſt. This word Chriſt is a Greeke word, and ſoundeth as much as Annointed in Engliſh. Whereas then we heare that our Sauiour is Chriſt that is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, we are aſſured that he is come into the world by the ſpeciall decree and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God himſelfe. The externall or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Oyle that was vſed in the time of the Lawe, God ordained for the creating or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing of three ſorts of officers, <hi>viz.</hi> Kings, Prieſts, and Prophets, whereby he did ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that by the hand of this King, he would gouerne and defend his people, in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this Prieſt, bee called vpon and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, and by the mouth of this Prophet, declare his wil and pleaſure vnto the people. Vnto all theſe Offices was our Sauiour an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, not with materiall or viſible oyle, but with the oyle of gladnes wherewith Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid Propheſied hee ſhould be annointed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue his fellowes. Neither beareth he theſe names and titles in vaine, but alſo hee execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Offices belonging thereunto: For firſt he hath deliuered vs, like a King, from the power of our enemies, and hath made vs
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:133395:30"/> free-men with the Angels in heauen, yea he hath giuen vs Lawes and Statutes to obſerue, which whoſo keepeth, ſhall liue in them: bleſſing alſo them that ſerue him, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſuch as rebell againſt him. Therefore in that we heare our Sauiour is annointed our King, to rule ouer vs, wee haue no little cauſe to reioyce, in that we may be aſſured, that the kingdome of darkneſſe, which our aduerſarie the diuell had begun to erect and ſtabliſh in vs, ſhall nowe bee ruinated and pluckt downe: In ſtead whereof Chriſt wil eſtabliſh his heauenly kingdome, which is iuſtice, peace, and ioy of the holy ghoſt: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that he ſhall bridle, with his might, and bruiſe with his rod of iron, not onely wicked and diueliſh men, but alſo the diuel himſelfe and al his Angels, which go about to hinder the increaſe of his glory, or our health and ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Secondarily, in that he is annointed our Prieſt, we haue this comfort giuen vnto vs, that we haue one that will ſacrifice continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, like good Iob for his children, and make interceſſion for vs. The office of the Prieſt in the time of the Lawe was, to pray for the people, to bleſſe them, to ſacrifice for them, to conſecrate and ſanctifie them according
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:133395:31"/> to the commandement. This was a great comfort in thoſe dayes, vnto the afflicted conſciences of diſtreſſed ſinners, groaning and groueling vnder the heauy burden of their manifold tranſgreſſions, to haue a Prieſt to pray for them, and to reconcile them vnto the fauour of God, whom by their ſinnes and iniquities they had prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vnto anger. Sithens then that we heare that Chriſt is annointed our Prieſt, we may aſſure our ſelues that hee is tied to the ſelfe ſame Offices; but indeed to ſo much more excellent then theſe, as he hath obtained a more excellent Prieſthood. The Prieſt after the order of Aron, ſerued in the corruptible and figuratiue Tabernacle; but our Prieſt is taken vp into the true Tabernacle, heauen it ſelfe, where he ſacrificeth for all the ſaints and ſeruants of God: there he maketh interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for vs, for hee aſcended thither, that he might follow all our ſuites faithfully and earneſtly. He bleſſeth vs alſo, in that he was made a curſe for vs: he ſacrificeth for vs, in that he offered vp himſelfe a ſacrifice once for all, for the ſinnes of the whole world: laſtly he ſanctifieth and conſecrateth his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike church, renewing hir minde, and waſhing hir in the fountain of regeneration
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:133395:31"/> by the word, that ſhe may be holy, euen as he is holy. Seeing then he is anointed of God, to ſacrifice and make interceſſion for vs, to bleſſe, conſecrate, and ſanctifie vs, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile vs againe into the fauour of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty god, that we may now without feare approach vnto him: what a ioyfull thing is this, that our Sauiour is a Prieſt?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, in that he was annointed to bee a prophet vnto vs, we may reioyce: and bee glad therein, becauſe we ſhall truely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand know the will and pleaſure of our God, ſeeing the Sonne of god himſelfe, who is one with his father, to whom the eternall will and counſell of God is manifeſt and open, is annointed and appointed to declare it vnto vs. And thus much of the Ioy which a ſinner may receiue when he vnderſtandeth that his Sauiour is Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thus (beloued) haue I acquainted you with the particularities of Ioy that occurre vnto vs in the meſſage of the Angel; what remaineth now? but that you ſhould ſing pſalmes of praiſe and thankſegiuing vnto god, who hath ſent theſe ioyfull Tidings vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs; Seeing he hath ſo gratiouſly regarded the low eſtate of vs his poore Creatures, as that he hath not ſpared his owne ſonne to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:133395:32"/> ſaue vs. Vnto which ſonne, if ye runne with penitent and contrite harts, though ye be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo heauy loaden, he will eaſe and refreſh you. You know, that in Adam ye were al a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lients from the houſe of God, but you heard how that in Chriſt ye are brought home vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the biſhop and ſhepheard of your ſoules; you did walke in darkeneſſe, but, Chriſt is come to giue you light, you haue mourned for your ſinnes, but a Sauiour is come to make you glad; you haue bin poore, but Chriſt is come with all the Treaſures of the Trinity to make you rich. You haue ſorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for beeing ſhut out of Paradiſe, but now Reioyce in that more then in any thing elſe; For as far as Adam, being in Paradiſe, did exceed vs in temporall bleſſings, ſo far do we out of Paradiſe exceed Adam in ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all benedictions: for though we were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to death for the tree of knowledge, yet Chriſt is come, that by the tree of his Croſſe wee might haue life, and that wee might haue it more aboundantly: more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly! what is that? that aboundantly we might haue more life by the Croſſe of Chriſt, then euer we had or could haue had by the tree of life, that aboundantly wee might gaine more by the obedience of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:133395:32"/> Chriſt in his death, then euer wee loſt or could looſe, by the diſobedience of Adam in his life: and therefore, though the ſinne of Adam was ſo heinous and horrible, that it caſt the Image of God out of Paradiſe, that it polluted all the race of mankinde, that it condemned the whole world, that it defaced the very frame of heauen it ſelfe; yet nowe conſidering the ſequele, how not onely the guilt of ſinne, but alſo the very memory of it is aboliſhed by the comming of Chriſt: we may not be afraid to ſay with S. Gregory, <hi>O faelix culpa quae talem ac tantum meruit ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere redemptorem.</hi> O happy man was Adam that euer he ſo ſinned and tranſgreſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, ſeeing both he and all we haue found ſuch plentiful redemption, ſuch ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable mercy, ſuch ſuperaboundant grace, ſuch felicity, ſuch eternity, ſuch life by one Sauiour. Wherefore (deere Chriſtian) what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou art, feare not any more as a man without hope, but let thy ſpirit reioyce in God thy Sauiour. Doe thy ſinnes greeue thee, and the puniſhment due vnto them ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie thy conſcience? Why, behold the Lamb of God that taketh away the ſinnes of the whole world: art thou ſtung with the old ſerpent Sathan? Looke then on the braſen
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:133395:33"/> ſerpent Chriſt, who healeth the ſting of the other: art thou hungry? Chriſt is borne the bread of life, of which whoſo eateth ſhall liue for euer: art thou thirſtie? behold Chriſt the fountaine of liuing water, of which who ſo drinketh ſhall thirſt no more; but it ſhall be vnto him a well of water ſpringing vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternall life: liueſt thou in darkneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Chriſt the light of the world, who one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſperſeth the cloudes of errour: art thou deſirous to enter into life? repaire vnto Chriſt, for he is the doore thereof, yea he is the way, the truth, and the life, without which way, there is no walking into heauen, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which truth, there is nothing but falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and errour, and without which life, there is nothing but death eternall. Seeing then that ſuch a Sauior is born vnto thee, in whom is the fulnes of al iov, how canſt thou be ſorrowfull, or how canſt thou feare? Shall Peter be ſad, when he ſeeth the boults of Iron beaten off from him by an Angel, and the gates of the priſon ſet open that he may go foorth and inioy his former freedome? Should Ionas feare a ſtorme when he was caſt vp ſafe on the land out of the belly of a whale? Or Sidrack Miſaack and Abednago mourne, beeing deliuered by the Lord from
<pb facs="tcp:133395:33"/> the fury of the furnace? Can Daniell but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce being ſaued from the Lions? Or Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph miſtruſt the goodnes of the Lord being promoted from a ſlaue, to be Lord of all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt? We are deliuered from a darker priſon then Peter, from a more fiery furnace then Sidrack, from a more cruell Lion then Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel, and adopted heires of a more noble kingdome then Joſeph was, euen the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Ieſus: how then ſhould we but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, being thus ſaued, and ſo highly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted? Why art thou heauy, O my ſoule, or why art thou at any time diſquieted within me? Liſt vp thy head, plucke vp a good cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage; celebrate with ioy the Natiuity of thy Sauiour; daunce now and be merry, not as Herodias did, but as Dauid did, leape vp in affection as high as heauen, where thy Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our now ſitteth, not in the lap of his mother, but on the right hand of his father in all glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and maieſtie. Come then, my brethren, let vs ſing vnto the Lord, let vs hartely reioyce in the ſtrength of our Saluation. Let Iſrael reioyce in him that made him, and let the children of Sion be ioyfull in their King: Praiſe his name in the daunce, ſing praiſes vnto him with Tabret and Harpe: Yong men and maidens, old men and children,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:133395:34"/> praiſe the name of the Lord, ſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Iuſtily vnto him with a good courage. For why? the Lord is knowne now to haue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in his people in that he hath receiued vs vnto mercy, and hath ſent his owne, Sonne to ſatisfie his Iuſtice, that wee might be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ued. He hath annointed him to be our King, let vs therefore obey him: he hath ordained him to be our Prieſt let vs therefore haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe vnto him: and hee hath appointed him to be our Prophet, let vs therefore har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and giue eare vnto him.</p>
            <p>O Lord God, how greatly are we indeb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto thy maieſty, being redeemed with ſo great a price, being ſaued ſo franckly and freely. O how art thou to be loued of vs poore creatures! how greatly art thou to be Reuerenced, honored, and glorified of vs? which haſt ſo exceedingly loued vs, ſaued vs, ſanctified and exalted vs; who exceeded all thy creatures in Rebellion againſt thee? We were vnworthy ſeruaunts, but now wee are made free, yea now wee are free indeed, in that thy ſonne hath made vs free. O giue vs thy grace to receiue thy ſonne being now come into the world; that we may be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of him in the world to come. And for this cauſe ſanctifie our ſinfull and polluted
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:133395:34"/> harts, that he may vouchſafe to enter into vs, and abide in vs; for a cleane Lord muſt haue a cleane habitation; That ſo beeing ſanctified in earthly Babilou we may bee thought worthy to be glorified in thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Ieruſalem. Heere there is but Tidings of Ioy, but there we ſhall enioy the Ioy it ſelfe. Heere there is but newes that he came, but there we ſhall reape the fruites of his comming, when we ſhall be wedded vnto him in ſpirituall vnity, and raigne with him in the kingdome of his deity; repleniſhed with that Ioy that no man ſhall take from vs. Of the which we beſeech thee, O father, to make vs pertakers and that for the merrits of that thy ſonne and our Sauiour through the mighty operation of the holy ghoſt. To which Trinity, yet one power and vnparted maieſty, wee aſcribe all honor and glory, praiſe and thankſgiuing, both now and euer. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
